Walls, Colette Collection of UAW District 65 Cornell Organizing Materials 6365
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Colette Walls Collection of UAW District 65 Cornell Organizing Materials
1980- 2014
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Walls, Colette
International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America
UAW District 65 Cornell Chapter
Active Concerned Employees (ACE)
6365
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Records.
Materials relating to the UAW organizing committees at Cornell University during the early 1980s.
8309519
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, December 18, 2013
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 27, 2015
Biographical / Historical
Colette Walls began working at Cornell University in June 1976. During the early part of 1980 she became involved with the UAW/District 65 Cornell union drive as a member of the organizing committee. Ms. Walls was also a member of the Clerical Organizing Committee working to organize the office workers. The significant goal in unionization for the Clerical unit was for women in those traditionally female jobs to have a say in the issues facing them: automation, occupational stress, low pay, low status, and lack of appreciation.
As part of the organizing effort Ms. Walls helped write newsletters and flyers, often drawing the cartoons for them, worked with focus groups, held informational meetings, and appeared on radio talk shows.
After the unsuccessful drive came to an end Ms. Walls continued on her Cornell career, retiring in 2013 as a department administrative manager.
Biographical / Historical
The Active Concerned Employees (ACE) committee was formed in early 1979 in an effort to improve the working life of Cornell employees. By 1980 their efforts began to take the form of unionization and ACE started an organizing campaign. District 65 initially led the drive, but as the drive progressed District 65 affiliated with UAW and by the end of the drive organizing at Cornell was clearly a UAW effort.
Althought the organizing drive initially included a wide array of employees differences in the card-signing rates led to a split. The service and maintenance employees were ready to vote for unionization by the end of 1980, well before the technical or the clerical and library employees were. The service and maintenance employees held a union election on February 24, 1981. The majority voted to unionize, forming UAW Local 2300. After difficult negotiations with the University, which included a strike, a contract was ratified in October, 1981.
Organizing continued with separate Technical Workers and Clerical Workers drives. Eventually the Technical Workers' drive had enough signatures to call for an election. Unionization was voted down in that election. The Clerical Workers' drive never reach the 30% threshold for signatures and was abandoned after over three years of effort.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists largely of the publications produced by the UAW organizing committees at Cornell University during the early 1980s. The best represented are "The Bear Facts" and "Clout!" There is only one issue of "Backbone." Also included is a narrative about the organizing effort, written by Colette Walls, who was active in the effort. There is also a 2006 interview with the professional organizer from the UAW, Barbara Rahke.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4252m: ILR School Student publication "The Cornell Worker" 5016: Cornell University Union Representation Material 5117: UAW-Cornell University Organizing Documents 5411 mf: Public Review Board Cases #11 & #48 on Microfilm 6094: UAW Public Review Boaard Decisions
Labor unions -- Organizing; Universities and colleges -- Employees -- Labor unions; Cupery, Steve; Davidoff, Al; Edelman, John; Edelman, Kurt; Lane, Carol; Livesay, Jane; Mackesey, Pam; Macomber, Jean; McPheeters, Jean; O'Conner, Chris; Rahke, Barbara; Reitz, Marlene; Rundle, Jim; Sexton, Brendon; Sirlin, Judy; Susselman, Sue; Tepperman, Jean; Valentino, Catherine; Walls, Colette; Weiss, Stephanie; Weldon, Cyd; York, Carolyn; Cornell University; District 65, Distribution Workers of America; International Union, United Automobile Workers of America (CIO); International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America. Local 2300 (Ithaca, N.Y.)
8309519
- Colette Walls Narrative, 2013-2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Brief history of UAW District 65 organizing at Cornell University. Includes a November 2013 draft and a February 2014 final copy.
- Barbara Rahke Interview, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Ms. Rahke was the UAW professional organizer sent to Cornell for the organizing effort
- Fact sheets (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Union fact sheets for distribution to Cornell employees and students
- Organizing Zone Map, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Cornell's Ithaca, NY, campus divided into organizing zones.
- Broadsides (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Advertising picnics and other events
- News clippings, 1980-2014 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  From the Cornell Daily Sun, The New York Times, and other publications
- Cornell UAW Cards (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Backbone, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  no.1 (1980:Sep.). Publication of the Cornell Chapter of UAW Service and Maintenance Organizing Committee
  - Item 1: Backbone, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Author: Cornell Chapter UAW Service and Maintenance Organizing Committee
    Notes: no.1 (1980:Sep.)
    Format: Publication
    Language: English.
- The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Publication of District 65 Cornell Chapter
  - Item 1: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Author: District 65 Cornell Chapter
    Notes: v.1 (1980:Mar.)
  - Item 2: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: no.2 (1980:Mar. 17)
  - Item 3: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: March 24, 1980.
  - Item 4: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: no.3 (1980:Apr.)
  - Item 5: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: no.4 (1980:Apr.)
  - Item 6: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: April 1980.
  - Item 7: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: no.5 (1980:May)
  - Item 8: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: no.6 (1980:May)
  - Item 9: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: no.7 (1980:June)
  - Item 10: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: no.8 (1980:June)
  - Item 11: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: no.9 (1980:July)
  - Item 12: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: v.10 (1980:Aug.)
  - Item 13: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: v.11 (1980:Aug.)
  - Item 14: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: no.12 (1980:Sep.)
  - Item 15: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: no.13 (1980:Oct.)
  - Item 16: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: no.14 (1980:Oct.)
  - Item 17: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: no.15 (1980:Nov.)
  - Item 18: The Bear Facts, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes: no.15 (1980:Dec.)
- The Bear Facts, 1981; Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Item 1: The Bear Facts, 1981; Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Notes: no.17 (1981:Jan.)
  - Item 2: The Bear Facts, 1981; Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Notes: no.17 (1981:Jan.). Copy 2.
  - Item 3: The Bear Facts, 1981; Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Notes: no.18 (1981:Feb.)
  - Item 4: The Bear Facts, 1981; Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Notes: no.19 (1981:Apr.)
  - Item 5: The Bear Facts, 1981; Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Notes: no.21 (1981:June)
  - Item 6: The Bear Facts, 1981; Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Notes: no.23 (1981:July)
  - Item 7: The Bear Facts, 1981; Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Notes: no.25 (1981:Sep.)
  - Item 8: The Bear Facts, 1981; Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Notes: no.26 (1981:oct.)
  - Item 9: The Bear Facts, 1981; Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Notes: no.27 (1981:Dec.)
- The Bear Facts, 1982; Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Item 1: The Bear Facts, 1982; Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Notes: no.28 (1982:Feb.)
  - Item 2: The Bear Facts, 1982; Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Notes: no.29 (1982:Feb. 24)
  - Item 3: The Bear Facts, 1982; Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Notes: no.30 (1982:Mar. 8)
  - Item 4: The Bear Facts, 1982; Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Notes: no.31 (1982:apr. 5)
  - Item 5: The Bear Facts, 1982; Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Notes: no.32 (1982:May)
  - Item 6: The Bear Facts, 1982; Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Notes: no.33 (1982:June)
  - Item 7: The Bear Facts, 1982; Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Notes: no.34 (1982:July/Aug.)
  - Item 8: The Bear Facts, 1982; Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Notes: no.35 (1982:Sep.)
  - Item 9: The Bear Facts, 1982; Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Notes: no.36 (1982:Oct.)
  - Item 10: The Bear Facts, 1982; Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Notes: no.37 (1982:Nov.)
  - Item 11: The Bear Facts, 1982; Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Notes: no.38 (1982:Dec.)
  - Item 12: The Bear Facts, 1982; Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Notes: Special 10th Anniversary Issue
- Clout!, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Publication of the UAW Clerical Organizing Committee
  - Item 1: Clout!, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Author: UAW Clerical Organizing Committee
    Notes: no.1 (1980:Sep. 1)
  - Item 2: Clout!, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Notes: no.2 (1980:Sep. 23)
  - Item 3: Clout!, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Notes: no.3 (1980:Oct.)
  - Item 4: Clout!, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Notes: no.5 (1980:Dec.)
  - Item 5: Clout!, 1981; Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Notes: no.6 (1981:Jan.)
  - Item 6: Clout!, 1982; Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Notes: March 1982.
  - Item 7: Clout!, 1983; Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Notes: April 1983. Special Issue for National Secretaries' Week
  - Item 8: Clout!, 1983; Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Notes: August 1983.
- Union Songs, Publication (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Two union song books
  - Item 1: Union Songs, Publication (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Item 2: Union Songs, Publication (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Notes: Sung by the Cornell/UAW Singing Bears
- UAW Publications, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Item 1: Solidarity, 1981; Publication (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Author: United Auto Workers (UAW)
    Notes: v.24:No.7 (1981:Aug.)
  - Item 2: UAW Ammo, 1982; Publication (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Notes: v.22:no.6 (1982:June)
- 60 Words A Minute and What Do You Get? Clerical Workers Today, Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
  By Jean Tepperman
  - Item 1: 60 Words A Minute And What Do You Get? Clerical Workers Today, Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Author: Jean Tepperman
- Cornell Chapter District 65, UAW, Publication (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Address listing
- Buttons, Publication (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Three union buttons (pins).
  - Item 1: Join UAW Vote: Organizing Committee, Memorabilia (Box 1, Folder 17)
    2.25 inch diameter button/pin
    Format: Memorabilia.
  - Item 2: Local 2300 UAW, Memorabilia (Box 1, Folder 17)
    1.5 inch diameter button/pin
  - Item 3: District 65 of the UAW Cornell Chapter, Memorabilia (Box 1, Folder 17)
    1.75 inch diameter button/pin with drawing of a Cornell bear on it.